[Music]
ear candles also known as ear cones are
promoted as a lowcost effective
treatment for ear wax they hollow tubes
of fabric impregnated with paraffin or
beeswax one end is placed in the
entrance to the ear canal and the other
end is lit after 15 minutes or so the
flame is extinguished and a brownish
waxy substance can be seen within the
remaining stub this is claimed to be ear
wax drawn out by some sort of vacuum
chimney effect but the same residue
presumably from the burning wax smoke
appears if you burn it alone outside the
ear researchers actually took the
additional step of running used ear
candle stubs through a mass spectrometer
and indeed no evidence of ear wax was
found not surprisingly perhaps since
tanom metric measurements showed no
signs of negative chimney effect
pressure at any point not to be
dissuaded proponents suggest that well
no ear wax maybe drawn out that day the
candling process at least heats up and
melts the ear wax which then comes out
naturally over the next few days but
Health Canada measured the air
temperature at the ear end of the
burning candle and the highest
temperature reach was only 72° fenhe
well below body
temperature though the purported
theories were found to be implausible
and demonstrably wrong the only way to
really tell if it works is to examine
the wax buildup in people before and
after ear candling photographs inside
the ear canal were taken before and
after ear candling Not only was no wax
removed but in some of the ear canals
candle wax was deposited so they ended
up worse than they were before uh not to
mention the recorded complications
including ear burs complete candle wax
blockage of ear canals eard drum
perforation infection and setting
people's hair on fire researchers
concluded ear candles have no benefit in
the management of ear wax and may result
in serious injury ear candles appear to
be a Triumph of ignorance over science
so what is effective for getting rid of
ear wax I'll cover that next
[Music]